Guide to the Stanley R. Rosenberg Architectural Records 1952-1985, undated, (bulk 1954-1974) PR 254
New-York Historical Society
Stanley R. Rosenberg Architectural Records
1952-1985, undated, (bulk 1954-1974)
New-York Historical Society
PR 254
3.22 Linear feet (6 boxes & 4 oversize folders)
Architect Stanley R. Rosenberg worked with several architectural firms, including Hausman & Rosenberg, designing a variety of buildings such as community centers, synagogues and high-rise office buildings.
Provenance
Gift of Stanley R. Rosenberg, 2006.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Stanley R. Rosenberg (b. 1923) attended Brooklyn College from 1941-1943 before obtaining his Bachelor of Architecture from Columbia University in 1952. He worked in several architectural firms before becoming a partner in Sirof & Rosenberg in 1954, which became Sirof, Rosenberg & Sivertsen in 1955. Rosenberg held an individual practice from 1958 to 1960. In July 1960 he joined with architect Alvin W. Hausman, forming Hausman & Rosenberg Architects. The two worked together on projects ranging from community centers to high-rise office buildings, until the firm dissolved in 1977.
Scope and Content Note
The Stanley R. Rosenberg Architectural Records span the period from 1952-1985 and primarily contains photographs, slides, negatives and printed material related to architectural projects designed by Rosenberg and his various architectural firms. Projects include apartment buildings, community centers, firehouses, hotels, offices, private residences, restaurants, schools, stores and synagogues. The collection is divided into three series: Stanley R. Rosenberg Project Files; Hausman & Rosenberg Project Files; and Office Files.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically by project name.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Additional architectural project and office files can be found in the following collections: Cass Gilbert Architectural Collection (PR 021), McKim, Mead & White Architectural Record Collection (PR 042) and George B. Post Architectural Record Collection (PR 052). Additional photographs by Richard Averill Smith can be found in the Mattie E. Hewitt & Richard A. Smith Photograph Collection (PR 026).
Correspondence.; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Dwellings -- United States -- Design and plans.; Fire stations.; Housing authorities.; Synagogues -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Commercial buildings -- United States -- Designs and plans.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Photographic prints.; Clippings (information artifacts); Architectural records.; Public buildings -- United States -- Design and plans.; Hausman, Alvin W.; Rosenberg, Stanley R.; Smith, Richard Averill
- Series I: Stanley R. Rosenberg Project Files
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Stanley R. Rosenberg Project Files contains photographs, slides, negatives and other printed material, mainly publicity, related to projects done by Stanley Rosenberg as well as the firms Sirof & Rosenberg and Sirof, Rosenberg & Sivertsen. Images include both photographs of finished projects as well as copy photographs of presentation drawings. Projects include Avenue Z Jewish Center & Talmud Torah, Harbor Hills Country Club, Manhasset Lakeville Firehouse, and Monaco Surf Club. Richard Averill Smith photographed the Harbor Hills Country Club; his negatives and prints are located in this series.
  Oversize material includes mounted photographs of the Canon Camera Showroom and the Harbor Hills Country Club and reproductions of presentation drawings for an unidentified commercial project as well as the Mack Residence. Oversize flat files contain two presentation drawings for Eastwood Village and one presentation aerial perspective drawing for the Hodson Community Center.
  Several 8" x 10" negatives from this series are severely deteriorated. These negatives have been separated for conservation reasons, and can be found in Box 5, Rehoused Negatives.
  - 6-8 East 53rd Street, New York, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - 30th Street Office Building, New York, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ardsley Motel, Ardsley, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    General note
    See also: Rehoused Negatives
  - Avenue Z Jewish Center & Talmud Torah, Brooklyn, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Azalea Inn, Norfolk, VA (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beth Jacob of Boro Park, Brooklyn, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Birer Residence, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Blackton's Fifth Avenue, various locations (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Botell's Clothing Store (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brownstone modernization (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Canon Camera Office & Showroom, New York, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clover Estates (Box Unknown container 573 for instance of Clover Estates, Folder unknown container)
    See: Rehoused Negatives
  - Eastwood Village, Centereach, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12-13)
    See also: Rehoused Negatives; Oversize Material-Flat Files
  - Elite Children's Clothing (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fashions for Girls, New York, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fifth Ave Card Shop, various locations (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gold Pure Food Building, Brooklyn, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Harbor Hills Country Club, Port Jefferson, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hodson Community Center, Crotona Bark, Bronx, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    See: Oversize Material-Flat Files
  - Hotel La Guardia, La Guardia Airport, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Karen Paul's Clothing Store (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Kingsbridge Center of Israel, Riverdale, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Krumholtz Bros. Warehouse (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lake Waubeeka Community Center, Lake Waubeeka, CT (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
  - Leban Residence, Hollywood, FL (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lisbon's Furniture (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lobel's Youth Center, various locations (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
  - Mack Residence, Great Neck, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
  - Manhasset Lakeville Firehouse, New Hyde Park, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Monaco Surf Club, Lido Beach, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
  - Office Building, Norfolk, VA (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
  - Patsy's Restaurant (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
  - Restaurant & Lounge, 18 Gramercy Park South, New York, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
  - School for Handicapped Children, Rockaway, NJ (Offsite-box 2, Folder 35)
  - Spinner's Self Service (Offsite-box 2, Folder 36)
  - "Taxpayer," Kings Highway (Offsite-box 2, Folder 37)
  - Torah Israel Community Center & Temple, Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 38)
  - Misc. & Unidentified Projects (Offsite-box 2, Folder 39)
- Series II: Hausman & Rosenberg Project Files
  Series II. Hausman & Rosenberg Project Files includes visual and printed material for projects designed by the firm of Hausman & Rosenberg. Copy negatives and photographs of presentation drawings make up the bulk of these files. Research material and slides of completed projects are also included. The firm designed animal hospitals, apartment buildings, libraries, office buildings, schools, and synagogues. Projects include the Lincoln Square Synagogue, Eleanor Roosevelt Houses and several branches of the Trade Bank & Trust Company.
  Oversize material includes photographs of Brookdale Institute for Talmudic Studies, Cryder House, the 1964 World's Fair Hell Drivers Exhibit, Trade Bank & Trust and Vitarine Pharmaceutical Branch. Presentation drawings include a reproduction of a drawing for the firm's Lido Beach Apartment project and original drawings of a storefront at 601 Madison Avenue and the Engine Co. 9, Ladder Co. 6 firehouse. A reproduction of a presentation drawing showing the Cryder House lobby is located in the Oversize flat files.
  - 160 Water Street, New York, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 40)
  - 215 West 125th Street, New York, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 41)
  - Appellate Court addition, New York, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 42)
  - Bier Veterinary Hospital (Offsite-box 2, Folder 43)
  - Bradley International Hotel (Offsite-box 2, Folder 44)
  - Branford Hills Apartments, Branford, CT (Offsite-box 2, Folder 45)
  - Brookdale Institute of Talmudic Studies of the Rabbi Jacob Joseph School, New York, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 46)
  - Brookdale Institute of Talmudic Studies of the Rabbi Jacob Joseph School, Riverdale, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 47)
  - Brooklyn Public Library, Greenpoint Branch, Brooklyn, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 48)
  - Camden office building, Camden, NJ (Offsite-box 2, Folder 49)
  - Camer Glass, Light fixture (Offsite-box 2, Folder 50)
  - Castle Hill Jewish Community Center, Bronx, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 51)
  - Congregation Sons of Israel, Yonkers, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 52)
  - Cryder House, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 53-54)
    See: Oversize Material; Oversize Material-Flat Files
  - Eleanor Roosevelt Houses, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, NY (Offsite-box 2, Folder 55)
  - Engine Co. 9, Ladder Co. 6, Firehouse, New York, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 56)
  - Floral Park Jewish Center, Floral Park, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 57)
  - Forest Park Jewish Center, Woodhaven, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 58)
  - Garden Jewish Center, Flushing, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 59)
  - Goldwater Memorial Hospital, Welfare Island, New York, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 60)
  - Greystone Jewish Center, Yonkers, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 61)
  - Hell Drivers Exhibit, 1964 World's Fair, Flushing, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 62)
    See: Oversize Material
  - Hillcrest Nursing Home, Spring Valley, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 63)
  - Lafayette Boynton Houses, Bronx, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 64)
  - Lido Beach Apartments, Lido Beach, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 65)
  - Lincoln Square Synagogue, New York, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 66)
  - Max & Rose Heller Hebrew Academy, Flushing, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 67)
  - Merrick-Bellmore Synagogue (Offsite-box 3, Folder 68)
  - Metro North Plaza, 101st Street, New York, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 69)
  - Middle Island Veterinary Hospital, Centereach, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 70)
  - Monterey Houses, Bronx, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 71)
  - North Bergen Research Center (Offsite-box 3, Folder 72)
  - Rabbi Dov Revel Yeshiva, Forest Hills, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 73)
  - River Plaza, MBH 134, Bronx, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 74)
  - Rockwood Park Jewish Center, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 75)
  - Sabbah Residence (Offsite-box 3, Folder 76)
  - Spring Valley Nursing Home (Offsite-box 3, Folder 77)
  - Sutton Plaza, Sutton Place, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 78)
  - Temple B'Nai Israel of Elmont (Offsite-box 3, Folder 79)
  - Temple Sholom (Offsite-box 3, Folder 80)
  - Trade Bank & Trust Company, 48th Street & Fifth Avenue, New York, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 81)
    (became National Bank of North America in 1970)
    See also: Oversize Material
  - Vitarine Pharmaceutical Branch, Laurelton, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 82)
  - West Hartford Animal Hospital, CT (Offsite-box 3, Folder 83)
  - Yeshiva of Eastern Parkway (Offsite-box 3, Folder 84)
  - Yeshivah Torah Vodaath, Harry Herskowitz School (Offsite-box 3, Folder 85)
  - Yeshivah Torah Vodaath & Mesvita, Dormitory (Offsite-box 3, Folder 86)
  - Young Israel of Co-op City, Bronx, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 87)
  - Young Israel of Scarsdale, Scarsdale, NY (Offsite-box 3, Folder 88)
  - Contact Sheets - Multiple Projects (Offsite-box 3, Folder 89)
- Series III: Office Files
  Series III. Office Files include articles, newspaper clippings, and reference images for various projects, from Rosenberg's various firms. Also included in these files are portraits of Stanley Rosenberg, correspondence, and paperwork related to Rosenberg's certification as a registered architect with the National Council of Architectural Registration Boards in various states.
  Oversize material included in this series has been separated and stored in flat file folders.
  - Articles written by Stanley R. Rosenberg, 1957-1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 90)
  - Artist Information, 1967, 1972, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 91)
    See also: Oversize Material-Flat Files
  - Artist Information - James Yu Gallery, 1971, 1973, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 92)
  - Consultation Services, 1966, 1968, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 93)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1957, 1970 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 94)
  - Curriculum Vitae, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 95)
  - Financial Records, 1969, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 96)
  - Job Lists, 1955, 1961, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 97)
  - Letters of Reference - Rosenberg & others, 1952, 1962, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 98)
  - National Council of Architectural Registration Boards,(NCARB) - California, 1964, 1975 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 99)
  - NCARB - Connecticut, 1963 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 100)
  - NCARB - Florida, 1969-1970, 1973 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 101)
  - NCARB - Massachusetts, 1964-1966, 1973 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 102)
  - NCARB - New Jersey, 1955-1956 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 103)
  - NCARB - New York, 1954-1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 104)
  - NCARB - Pennsylvania, 1953 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 105)
  - NCARB - Virginia, 1955, 1959, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 106)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1961, 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 107)
    See also: Oversize Matieral-Flat Files
  - Notes for Radio Shows/Interviews, 1965, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 108)
  - Office Forms - Templates, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 109)
  - Portraits - Stanley R. Rosenberg, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 110)
  - Press Releases & Radio Appearance Schedules, 1965, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 111)
  - Reference Images, n.d. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 112)
- From Series I: Stanley R. Rosenberg Project Files, [1952-1962]
  Rehoused Negatives contains 8" x 10" negatives that are severely deteriorated, difficult to handle and to view, and cannot be reproduced. These negatives have been separated for conservation reasons, and can be found in Box 5.
  Oversize photographs and presentation drawings in this series have been separated. Presentation drawings larger than 16 x 20 inches can be found in Oversize Flat Files.
  - REHOUSED NEGATIVES
    - Ardsley Motel, Ardsley, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 113)
    - Clover Estates (Offsite-box 5, Folder 114)
    - Eastwood Village, Centereach, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 115)
    - Hotel La Guardia, La Guardia Airport, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 116)
    - Kingsbridge Center of Israel, Riverdale, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 117)
    - Mack Residence, Great Neck, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 118)
    - Manhasset Lakeville Firehouse, New Hyde Park, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 119)
    - Monaco Surf Club, Lido Beach, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 120)
    - Restaurant & Lounge, 18 Gramercy Park South, New York, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 121)
    - Torah Israel Community Center & Temple, Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn, NY (Offsite-box 5, Folder 122)
  - OVERSIZE MATERIAL
    - Canon Camera Showroom (Offsite-box 6, Folder 123-124)
    - Harbor Hills Country Club, Port Jefferson, Long Island, NY (Offsite-box 6, Folder 125)
    - Presentation Drawings (Offsite-box 6, Folder 126)
  - OVERSIZE MATERIAL-FLAT FILES
    - Presentation Drawings (Box Unknown container 574 for instance of Presentation Drawings, Folder OS-1)
- From Series II: Hausman & Rosenberg Project Files, [1960-1974]
  Oversize photographs and presentation drawings in this series have been separated. Material larger than 16 x 20 inches can be found in Oversize Flat Files.
  - OVERSIZE MATERIAL
    - Brookdale Institute for Talmudic Studies of the Rabbi Jacob Joseph School, New York, NY (Offsite-box 6, Folder 127)
    - Cryder House, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 6, Folder 128)
    - Hell Drivers Exhibit, 1964 World's Fair, Flushing, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 6, Folder 129)
    - Trade Bank & Trust Company, 48th Street & Fifth Avenue, New York, NY (Offsite-box 6, Folder 130)
    - Vitarine Pharmaceutical Branch, Laurelton, Queens, NY (Offsite-box 6, Folder 131)
    - Contact Sheets - Multiple Projects (Offsite-box 6, Folder 132)
    - Presentation Drawings (Offsite-box 6, Folder 133)
  - OVERSIZE MATERIAL - FLAT FILES
    - Presentation Drawings (Box Unknown container 575 for instance of Presentation Drawings, Folder OS-2)
- From Series III: Office Files, 1952-1985, n.d.
  Oversize material included in this series has been separated and stored in flat file folders. This material includes newspaper clippings, articles and unidentified floor plans for an private residence.
  - OVERSIZE MATERIAL-FLAT FILES
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1963-1965, 1980 (Box Unknown container 576 for instance of Newspaper Clippings, Folder OS-3)
    - Miscellaneous Material, n.d. (Box Unknown container 577 for instance of Miscellaneous Material, Folder OS-4)